Dr. rer. nat. Martin Bies

Curriculum Vitae



SUMMARY

I hold a **PhD in Physics** ($Heidelberg\ Univ.,\ 2018$), specializing in **string** theory and mathematics. My research is inspired by computational analysis of massless spectra in string vacua, resulting in publications on toric geometry, Freyd categories, Brill-Noether theory, and root bundles. Proficient in julia, C++, and python, I excel in open**source software development** (*git*) to advance **computational research**. My diverse expertise emphasizes my interdisciplinary commitment. With a history of international collaborations, full English proficiency, and extensive teaching experience, I showcase a versatile skill set.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM 10/2022 (FT)

Mathematics Dept., RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, Germany Postdoctoral Researcher

I work on the OSCAR computer algebra system (https://www.oscarsystem.org/). My work enhances toric geometry capabilities and develops tools for string theory geometries using advanced algebraic geometry techniques. I have added 78,000+ lines and modified 59,000+ lines.

09/202I - 08/2022 (FT)

Dept. of Phys. & Astron., University of Pennsylvania, USA Simons Postdoctoral Fellow

Studied with M. Cvetič & R. Donagi *F-theory QSMs* via root bundles.

09/2020 - 08/202I (FT)

Dept. of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania, USA Simons Postdoctoral Fellow

Work with M. Cvetič and R. Donagi on root bundles in string theory.

IO/2019 - 09/2020 (FT)

Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, UK Long Term Visitor

Follow-up of Wiener-Anspach project (initiated at PTM, Brussels).

10/2018 - 09/2019 (FT)

PTM, Université Libre de Bruxelles, Belgium Postdoctoral Researcher

M/F-Theory: SCFT Design (funded by Foundation Wiener-Anspach).

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau Department of Mathematics

Gottlieb-Daimler-Straße 48

Office 48-407 67663 Kaiserslautern

Germany

December 15, 1987

German

+49 (0)631 205 2252 bies@mathematik.uni-kl.de

https://martinbies.github.io/ https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9609-1693

https://github.com/HereAround

https://www.linkedin.com/in/martin-bies-000a1156/

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE CONT.

02/2018 - 09/2018 (FT)

ITP, Heidelberg University, Germany Postdoctoral Researcher

Cluster of Excellence EXC 2181 STRUCTURES.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor for Comp. Linear Algebra 2021, 2022

University of Pennsylvania, USA

Senior Tutor 2016, 2018

Heidelberg University, Germany

Tutor in 8 courses 2012 - 2018

Heidelberg University, Germany

EDUCATION

03/2014 - 02/2018 PhD in Physics (Grade: MCL)

> ADVISOR: T. WEIGAND & M. BARAKAT Heidelberg University, Germany

Master of Physics (Grade: 1.0) 09/2012 - 02/2014

ADVISOR: T. WEIGAND

Heidelberg University, Germany

Bachelor of Physics (Grade: 1.1) 10/2008 - 08/2012

ADVISOR: T. WEIGAND

Heidelberg University, Germany

SCHOLAR SHIPS

09/2020 - 08/2022

10/2018 - 09/2020

01/2010 - 02/2018

10/2010 - 06/2011

Simons Postdoctoral Fellow Foundation Wiener-Anspach Studienstiftung des dt. Volkes ERASMUS exchange student

Imperial College, London, UK

LANGUAGES

German English French

Native **Full Proficiency Intermediate** (CEFR Level B_I)



PUBLICATIONS

- M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Improved Statistics for F-theory Standard Models, Preprint, https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02535.
- M. Bies, Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models, Preprint, https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08144.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry in OSCAR*, Computeralgebra Rundbrief, https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08110.
- M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Brill-Noether-general Limit Root Bundles: Absence of vector-like Exotics in F-theory Standard Models, Journal of High Energy Physics, DOI: 10.1007/JHEPII(2022)004.
- **M. Bies**, M. Cvetič, M. Liu, *Statistics of Root Bundles Relevant for Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs*, Physical Review D, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.104.L061903.
- **M. Bies**, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Liu, M. Ong, *Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs*, Journal of High Energy Physics, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP09(2021)076.
- M. Bies, S. Posur, Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors, Journal of Algebra and Its Applications, DOI: 10.1142/s0219498822501869.
- M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, L. Ling, M. Liu, F. Ruehle, *Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP01(2021)196.
- **M. Bies**, Cohomologies of Coherent Sheaves and Massless Spectra in F-theory, Heidelberg University Library, DOI: 10.11588/HEIDOK.00024045.
- M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, *Algebraic Cycles and Local Anomalies in F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, DOI: 10.1007/jhepii(2017)100.
- **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, *Gauge Backgrounds and Zero-Mode Counting in F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)081.
- **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, C. Pehle, T. Weigand, *Chow Groups, Deligne Cohomology and Massless Matter in F-theory*, Preprint, https://arxiv.org/abs/1402.5144.

RECORD OF TEACHING EXPERIENCE

01/2022 - 05/2022	Instructor for Computational Linear Algebra (University Of Pennsylvania, USA)
01/2021 - 05/2021	Instructor for Computational Linear Algebra (University Of Pennsylvania, USA)
04/2018 - 10/2018	Senior tutor for <i>Methods of Mathematical Physics 1</i> (Heidelberg University, Germany)
10/2016 - 03/2017	Tutor for Theoretical Physics I (Heidelberg University, Germany)
04/2016 - 09/2017	Senior tutor for General Relativity (Heidelberg University, Germany)
04/2015 - 09/2015	Tutor for Theoretical Physics IV (Heidelberg University, Germany)
10/2014 - 03/2015	Tutor for <i>Quantum Field Theory</i> (Heidelberg University, Germany)
10/2013 - 03/2014	Tutor for Theoretical Physics III (Heidelberg University, Germany)
04/2013 - 09/2013	Tutor for Theoretical Physics II (Heidelberg University, Germany)
10/2012 - 03/2013	Tutor for Theoretical Physics I (Heidelberg University, Germany)

CONFERENCES, TALKS AND POSTERS

07/2023	Talk at Third Annual Meeting 2023 of SFB-TRR 195 (Saarbruecken, Germany) Talk title: F-Theory: Exemplifying OSCAR's Pursuit for Multidisciplinary Excellence
07/2023	Talk and Poster at <i>StringMath 2023</i> (Melbourne, Australia) Talk title: <i>Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models</i> Poster title: FTheoryTools – <i>A Computer Tool for Singular Elliptic Fibrations</i>
07/2023	Talk at <i>StringPheno 2023</i> (Daejeon, South Korea) Talk title: <i>Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models</i>
05/2023	Talk at <i>Computeralgebra Tagung 2023</i> (Hannover, Germany) Talk title: <i>F-Theory Tools: String theory Applications of OCSAR</i>
05/2023	Talk at Oberseminar algebraische Geometrie (Saarbruecken, Germany)

	Talk title: F-Theory and Singular Elliptic Fibrations
07/2022	Strings 2022 (Vienna, Austria)
07/2022	Talk at <i>String Math 2022</i> (Warsaw, Poland) Talk title: <i>Towards F-theory MSSMs</i>
07/2022	Talk at <i>String Pheno 2022</i> (Liverpool, England) Talk title: <i>Towards F-theory MSSMs</i>
06/2022	Simons Collaboration on Homological Mirror Symmetry Geometry, Topology and Singular Special Holonomy Spaces (Freiburg, Germany)
11/2021	Simons Collaboration on Homological Mirror Symmetry Annual Meeting (New York, United States)
09/2021	Talk at Summer series on string phenomenology Talk title: Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs
09/2021	Simons Collaboration on Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis, and Physics Progress and Open Problems (Stony Brook, United States)
09/2021	Simons Collaboration on Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis and Physics Annual Meeting (New York, United States)
07/2021	String Pheno 2021 (virtual conference)
06/2021	Strings 2021 (virtual conference)
06/2021	String Math 2021 (virtual conference)
12/2020	Talk at String Data 2020 (virtual conference) Talk title: Vector-like spectra in F-theory (joined with M. Liu)
10/2020	Talk (Philadelphia, United States) Talk title: <i>Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory</i>
06/2020	Talk at Summer series on string phenomenology Talk title: On Stratification Diagrams, Algorithmic Spectrum Estimates and Vector-Like Pairs in F-theory
06/2020	String Pheno 2020 (virtual conference)
12/2019	Talk (Philadelphia, United States) Talk title: From F-theory Standard Models to Freyd Categories and back
09/2019	Poster at Strings and Geometry (Oxford, United Kingdom) Poster title: Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors
08/2019	Talk at gap singular meeting and school (Lambrecht, Germany) Talk title: Monoidal Structures in Freyd Categories
07/2019 10/2018	Strings 2019 (Brussels, Belgium) Talk (Brussels, Belgium) Talk title: Counting Massless Matter in F-theory with CAP
08/2018	Talk at CAP_days 2018 (Siegen, Germany) Talk title: CAP, Machine Learning and String Theory
05/2018	Talk in seminar on <i>Holography and Large-N duality</i> (Heidelberg, Germany) Talk title: <i>Conformal Invariants; Fefferman–Graham Expansion; Graham–Lee Theorem</i> (with Menelaos Zikidis)
03/2018	String Data 2018 (Munich, Germany)
07/2017	Talk at <i>String Pheno 2017</i> (Virginia, USA) Talk title: <i>Zero Mode Counting in F-Theory via</i> CAP
12/2015	String Math 2015 (Sanya, China)
09/2015	Third GAP Days (Trondheim, Norway)
03/2015	Second GAP Days (Aachen, Germany)
02/2015	Physics and Geometry of F-Theory (Munich, Germany)
12/2014	Homological Perturbation Theory (Galway, Ireland)
08/2014	Talk at GAP Days (Aachen, Germany)

Talk title: String Theory, Sheaf Cohomology and the homalg Package

07/2014 Talk (Aachen, Germany)

Talk title: The Standard Model from String Theory

05/2014 Talk at seminar series What is? (Heidelberg, Germany)

Talk title: What is a Fermion/Boson (in Quantum Mechanics)?

02/2014 Geometry and Physics of String Compactifications (Heidelberg, Germany)

02/2014 Talk (Heidelberg, Germany)

Talk title: Cohomology of Holomorphic Pullback Line Bundles on Smooth and Compact Normal Toric Varieties

05/2012 **Talk** (Heidelberg, Germany)

Talk title: Intersecting D6-Brane Models

ENGAGEMENT AT STUDIENSTIFTUNG DES DEUTSCHEN VOLKES

06/2018 Member of the admission board Heidelberg
 12/2017 Member of the admission board Ellwangen III
 05/2017 Training for admission board members – successfully completed
 11/2016 Member of the admission board Heidelberg

REFERENCES

Dr. Mirjam Cvetič

POSITION Fay R. and Eugene L. Langberg Professor
EMPLOYER Department of Physics and Astronomy

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL cvetic@physics.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8153

Dr. Ron Donagi

POSITION Thomas A. Scott Professor of Mathematics

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL donagi@math.upenn.edu

PHONE +I (215) 898 8465

Dr. Max Horn

POSITION Professor

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, Germany

EMAIL horn@mathematik.uni-kl.de

PHONE +49 63I 205 2730